<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The beast is wounded. Or Information from Scotland, concerning their reformation Wherein is breifly declared, the true cause and ground of all the late troubles there; and the reasons why they have rejected the bishops, with their courts, canons, ceremonies and service-booke. Hereto is added some fruitfull observations, upon the former declaration: by Io: Bastwicks younger brother. The first part.</title>
            <title>Beast is wounded.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11740</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22032</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116914</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852129</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17436</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11740)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17436)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 396:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The beast is wounded. Or Information from Scotland, concerning their reformation Wherein is breifly declared, the true cause and ground of all the late troubles there; and the reasons why they have rejected the bishops, with their courts, canons, ceremonies and service-booke. Hereto is added some fruitfull observations, upon the former declaration: by Io: Bastwicks younger brother. The first part.</title>
                  <title>Beast is wounded.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Richt Right Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yeare that the bishops had their downefall in Scotland [i.e. 1638]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Identification of printer and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>No more printed.</note>
                  <note>The Confession of Faith was intended to be bound between quires B and C, but is frequently missing or misbound; the various editions are catalogued separately as STC 22026-7.</note>
                  <note>In this edition title page line 14 has "IUDG." [italic].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17436:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17436:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>BEAST IS WO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NDED.</hi> OR <hi>Information from Scotland, concerning their Reformation.</hi> Wherein Is breifly declared, the true cauſe and ground of all the late Troubles there; and the reaſons why they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the Biſhops, with their Courts, Canons, Ceremonies and Service-booke. <hi>Hereto Is added ſome fruitfull obſervations, upon the former declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: by Io: Baſtwicks younger Brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JVDG.</hi> 5.31.</bibl>
               <p>So let thine Enemies periſh, O Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>The first part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the yeare that the <hi>Biſhops</hi> had their downefall in SCOTLAND.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17436:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>COurteous Reader; it is a note as the <hi>Wiſe-man,</hi> noteth it, of a <hi>foole, to beleeve every thing:</hi> I doubt not but thou haſt heard much of the Troubles in Scotland; Now, that thou mayſt not <hi>juſtifie the wicked, and condemne the juſt, which are both abomination to the Lord.</hi> I have thought fitt, for thy good, to publ ſh this ſhort relation: It came to me from ſuch perſons, as doe well know the proceedings of things there, from first to laſt; and therefore thou mayſt be confident that the ſame is trùe.</p>
            <p>It ſeemes by ſome notes which I finde in the margent, that it was ſent from a <hi>Scotſman,</hi> to ſome good freind that he had in England: and in likelihood a ſtrict <hi>Nonconformiſt,</hi> who ſhewes his good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that <hi>England</hi> might bè reduced unto <hi>Scotlands</hi> Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and not <hi>Stotland</hi> to <hi>Englands</hi> Deformation: But not beeing willing to write of things whereof I have no cerraine know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I will therefore be ſilent, and leave thee to the reading of the diſcourſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17436:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the deſire of <hi>King Iames</hi> (by whoſe inſtigation I know not<note n="(a)" place="margin">It was ſome <hi>Biſh</hi> a thouſand to one elſe. For what miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe is there, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if done againſt the true worſhip of God, but theſe <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Earth</hi> have their ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in it. See <hi>Syons-plea; A Looking glaſse for the Prelates;</hi> the <hi>Abreviate, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> that the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> would admitt, that ſuch men as ſtood Miniſters, to thoſe Churches, which in the time of <hi>Poperie</hi> were called <hi>Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks,</hi> might have the Title of <hi>Lord-Biſhops,</hi> and voyces in Parliament.<note n="(b)" place="margin">Parliaments will doe better without theſe men. For they well reſemble, that filthy bird, which caries this motto: <hi>contactu omnia faedat</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>To this the people conſented,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Better they had not; for they have ſmarted for it ever ſince, as their owne relation here mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth. As the <hi>Tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians</hi> in conſenting to take the <hi>Horſe</hi> into their Citie, had their citie ſpoyled by it: So from the <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> (as out of the <hi>Troians Horſes belly</hi>) hath iſſued the cauſe &amp; ground of al their late troubles. Se <hi>Pro.</hi> 29 2.</note> and in the yeare 1602. it was by a Parliament confirmed; Yet ſo, as with certaine <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſoes</hi> and conditions, then and there expreſſed: That is, that all ſuch as were then reſident in ſuch places; and all ſuch as afterwards ſhould happen to be preſented to them, ſhould by ſolemne Oath, and publick ſubſcription, ſweare and be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, neither to propound nor give conſent to any thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in Parliament, without a precedent Commiſſion of a generall aſſembly. Moreover, that they ſhould not pretend any authority or juriſdiction above other Miniſters, and that they ſhould be as lyable and ſubject as any other Miniſters to the Sentence and Cenſure of <hi>Preſbyteries, Provinciall and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Synods:</hi> To bee ſhort, if they tranſgreſſed either againſt thoſe rules, or any other inſtitution, which the Church tyed them unto, they might be (and ſhould be) excommunicated by the <hi>Preſ-bytery and Synod,</hi> and depoſed <hi>a beneficio &amp; officio.</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Jf we had ſuch Law with us in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; executed, we ſhould not be troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led long with <hi>Bb</hi> nor any of that <hi>Brood</hi> downward to the <hi>Parater.</hi> For their blaſphemies; treaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, murders, &amp;c are ſo obvious to all mens eyes. As the ſevereſt puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in any civil Court would be light enought to be laid upon them. See <hi>Quench-Coale; Epiſt. Remonſt.</hi> the laſt <hi>Parl.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Howſoever at the firſt thus they were ſworne to doe: And were admitted no otherwiſe, neither upon other tearmes,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17436:3"/>but what is before expreſſed: Notwithſtanding they having gotten a footing, it was not long ere they brake their Oath, and attempted many unlawful actions, to the great diſhonour of Gods name, the ſcandall of the Goſpell, and to the likely diſſipation of the whole Church, had not the Lord prevented it, by a wonderfull deliverance.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Such <hi>a deliverance</hi> God grant England; and when we ſee it, we will ſay; <hi>thy right hand, O Lord, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come glorious in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, thy right hand, O Lord, hath daſhed in peeces the enemies;</hi> and good cauſe too for this would prove to our Land a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bleſſing then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>was our deliverance from the <hi>Gunpowder treaſon.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee would nor faile to keepe a day of thankeſgiving in remembrance of it; as did the Iewes, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Hamon</hi> and his Sonnes were hangd.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It would required a large volume, to ſet downe all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular evils and troubles, which thoſe <hi>Lordly Prelates</hi> brought upon that Church; And more would have brought, had not <hi>their hornes</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">By the <hi>Hornes of the Beaſt,</hi> is meant the Antichriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, which they exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe over their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; By which (as a Beaſt with hornes, they puſh the godly ſometime into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, other-while to the Pillary, many times into forreigne Countries; ſo that un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>till theſe hornes bee cut off, there is no keeping houſe with them.</note> beene cut off. Among other acts of their <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government,</hi> they tooke upon them to depoſe Miniſters as they pleaſed, and when they pleaſed: And admitted ſundry ſcandalous perſons<note n="(c)" place="margin">The Prelates in Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d never ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much prophanes this way, as ours have done; For whereas, idolaters, adulterers, lyars, forcerers, whoremonngers, theeves drunkards, <hi>&amp; quid non,</hi> are allowed and liked off; On the contrary, they ſuppreſſe all them, who will not be their <hi>Drudges,</hi> to ſerve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and their great <hi>Landlord</hi> the Pope; witnes <hi>Wren</hi> the <hi>Norridge Beaſt.</hi> See the <hi>unbiſh: of Timot. and Tit.</hi>
               </note> (like themſelves) to the Miniſtery, and chardge of Soules; And kept back from the Miniſtery all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and able men, what they could. And not contented with this, they procured from the <hi>King</hi> a warrant, under the ſhew or pretence whereof, they ſilenced the moſt Godly, learned and faithfull Miniſters in the Kingdome: And alſo by the ſame authorities they brought into the Church many Popiſh Ceremonies, to the generall greife of the godly, both there, and in many other places.</p>
            <p>And theſe great abuſes of theirs, they brough the ſooner &amp; eaſier to paſſe, in regard there were ſome Courtiers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers about his Majeſtie, that were Popiſhly affected, and <hi>bore ill will to Sion:</hi> this is cleare in the cauſe of <hi>Melvin, Forbes, Bruce,</hi> and others <hi>Worthies</hi> of that Church who were exiled<note n="(d)" place="margin">Doth the Church of Scotland reckon it for one of her greevan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that they have unjuſtly baniſhed ſome of her Miniſters; How then would they have taken it, had they ſeene them whipt in their ſtreetes: ſtood on Pillaries, burnd-marked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> about the time that the <hi>Earl of Northhamton</hi> and <hi>B. Bancroft</hi> had greateſt acceptation with <hi>K: Iames:</hi> Soe againe when the 5. <hi>Articles</hi> were introduced by a moſt illegall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious and violent way in the <hi>Aſsembly</hi> at <hi>Perth,</hi> who were then preſent with the King, but <hi>Buckingam</hi> and <hi>B. Land,</hi> twoſit inſtruments as could bee, to bring ſuch an evill worke to paſſe.</p>
            <p>They having thus begun to ſpoyle the <hi>Lords Vineard,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards they cauſed many idle pamphlets to be publiſhed,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17436:3"/>againſt that <hi>good old way,</hi> of Government<note n="(a)" place="margin">Our Bb. have a trick which the <hi>Scot.</hi> never uſed, that is to caſt men into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of all meanes of writing and then ſer then Paraſites and Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phants to rayle aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt them; Now tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe are wiſe in their generation, or they know had their oppoſites the liberty that they have, they were better be ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gd out of the way, then ſuffer the juſt ſhame which they would doe, for their filthy lies &amp; blaſphentiess.</note> of that Church; by which Government before their Lordſhips ruled, the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Doctrines, and ill liues of Preachers were ſeverely cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and ſuppreſſed; But for their parts, they gave way and liberty, unto <hi>evill doers,</hi> and ſought only to curbe and ſuppreſſe the better ſort.</p>
            <p>Add hereunto their procuring from the <hi>K:</hi> a warrant for to exerciſe ſuch a juriſdiction in the civil Government<note n="(b)" place="margin">Forgs (the Tipe of <hi>Bb.</hi>) are ſaid to have 2 <hi>ſmall threads</hi> hanging neere their eyes, wherwith they make trapps, &amp; lay them in muddy pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, for to devoure the Fiſh; theſe <hi>tove threads</hi> ſignifie the <hi>civill</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall functions of</hi> Bb. wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with (as the <hi>Frog</hi> with her <hi>tvvo threads</hi>) they take the godly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure them.</note> as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with the Lawes of that Relame, the honour of the Soveraigne; &amp; peace of that Country: Nay, not here withall are ſatisfyed, but ſeeke further for a Commiſſion from <hi>King Charles,</hi> and under ſhew or colour of which warrant<note n="(c)" place="margin">As the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſees</hi> never left <hi>Pilate,</hi> till he had paſſed ſentence of death againſt <hi>Chriſt:</hi> So the <hi>Prelates</hi> are earneſtly importunate with the Kings of the Earth, to have <hi>Commiſſion</hi> and <hi>vvarrant</hi> from them, for to crucifie Chriſt dayly in his members.</note> they make many greevious acts of injuſtice, and greatly oppreſſe many of his Majeſties loyall &amp; good ſubjects.<note n="(d)" place="margin">If you complaine of oppreſſion, and thinke you have juſt cauſe for it, to <hi>vvound the Beaſt;</hi> What may wee ſay of our <hi>oppreſſions,</hi> which are more for number, more heinous for nature, longer for continuance, and more common and generall. For what condition is there of men, among us, but are horribly abuſed by them. See the <hi>Abbreviate.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe abuſes are not all, for beſides they have <hi>(vys &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis)</hi> uſed meanes to gert another Commiſſion from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, whereby to cover their unlawfull wayes unto benefices, for themſelves and their freinds: and withall got a colour of <hi>an Act of Parliament,</hi> to bring the <hi>Surpluſse</hi> into the Church, they cauſed fome <hi>Popiſh Lords</hi> to ſit upon the <hi>Articles of the Parliament An:</hi> 1633. they were alſo the inſtruments that procured an act to be contrived, beeing <hi>a racification of the Kings prerogative and power to impoſe ſuch apparell upon Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in divine ſervice, as he ſhould thinke ſu;</hi> Yea and to bring this to paſſe, they moved the King to preſſe all men, either to conſent or diſſent to the <hi>whole</hi> Act, as it was framed, thereby cunningly to draw all the <hi>Parliament-men</hi> either to deny the <hi>K: prerogative,</hi> or elſe to conſent to their plott for the <hi>Surpluſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More then this, they perſwaded his Majeſty to ſett downe with his owne hand, the names of all the Noblemen that ſhould diſcent from the aforeſaid Act; and that they ſhould be taken as men diſreſpecting his Majeſty and his Service, and that hee ſhould not heare them to give any reaſon for their diſlike of the thing: And whereas there was found after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with the Lord <hi>Balmerin:</hi> a certaine writing containing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17436:4"/>ſome reaſons wherefore the Noblemen could not aſcent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſaid Act; And ſome other paſſages, expedient to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate their perſons and cariages from the reproach of beeing diſ-affectionated to his Majeſties Service, and this ſet downe in a <hi>Potition,</hi> with an intent that it ſhould be preſented to the King, by the Noblemen, but was not. The Biſhops getting a ſight of this Copie, according to the reſt of their doings, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this good Nobleman for having this Perition to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of <hi>Legis Majeſtatis;</hi> And it went neere with his life.<note n="(a)" place="margin">Our <hi>Engliſh Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates</hi> this way are <hi>None-ſuch;</hi> For if they perceive a man to bee an enemie to their unbleſſed King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, they will bee ſure to have his blood for it if they can: &amp; this our Noblitie know well enough, the which makes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the unwillinger, to power out their vials upon <hi>the throne of the Beaſt.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Their Lordſhips having gone thus farre, are not affraid to publiſh a Booke of moſt wicked <hi>Canons,</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Conſider O <hi>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> what cauſe thou haſt to free thy ſelfe, out of the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of theſe <hi>theeves</hi> &amp; <hi>murderers,</hi> who have many yeares bound thee, (as Tyrants and Turkes doe <hi>Gally-ſlaves</hi> to their oars;) I ſay bound thee with their <hi>Canons, Articles, Injunctions</hi> (as ſo many irons &amp; fetters) to row for them, <hi>Romes Boat.</hi> So that Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bath nor the cauſe which thou haſt, to putt thoſe <hi>Amalekites</hi> to the ſword.</note> among which, one is, <hi>that whoſoever ſhall affirme that the Service-booke</hi> (which was not yet out but in hatching) <hi>containes any thing erronious, ſhall be excommunicated, ipſo facto.</hi> it was not long after this, ere they cauſed the ſaid <hi>Service-booke</hi> to be publiſhed. Which hath in it, not only the Superſtition and Popery contained in the <hi>Engliſh Leiturgis,</hi> but ſome thing more; and that they might bring the Church <hi>(nolens volens)</hi> to uſe this <hi>Jdol-booke,</hi> they procured a Proclamation<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quae:</hi> whether the Scotſmen did well, to refuſe the <hi>Service-booke,</hi> being commaunded by the <hi>K.</hi> to uſe it; <hi>&amp; quid ſequitur.</hi>
               </note> to be publiſhed, wherein al his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties (ſubjects were commanded, to conforme ſtrictly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as to the only forme of Gods publick worſhip for that Church.</p>
            <p>Beeing thus ſwollen<note n="(d)" place="margin">Nor like <hi>Ours:</hi> For their inſolencies are intollerable; ſpecially that <hi>little great Laud;</hi> but this gives me hope, that their ſhame &amp; fall is at hand; droſſe aſſoon as ever it hath gotten up to the top, and elevated it ſelfe above the pure mettall, is then ſcummed off &amp; caſt away; Theſe like droſſe &amp; ſcumme are riſen up, above their betters; therefore &amp;c. See <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119 199.</note> with a preſumptuous conceit of their power, and thinking now that neither great nor ſmall, had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the courage or wiſedom to ſtand in their way<note n="(e)" place="margin">As the <hi>Scots Bb.</hi> were deceived, ſo I truſt will <hi>Ours</hi> be.</note> the <hi>Biſhop of Ederb:</hi> in <hi>July</hi> 1637. gives order, to the Miniſters of that Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they read the aforeſaid <hi>Service-booke</hi> in their Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatious: Which would be ſuch a <hi>Maſse</hi> in Scotland as the Pope himſelfe.<note n="(f)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pope Pius</hi> 4 ſent <hi>Vincentio Parpatia Abbot of S. Saviours</hi> to Qu. Eliz: offering her to confirme the <hi>Engliſh Leiturgy,</hi> if ſhe would yeeld to him in ſome other things. <hi>Cambden in An.</hi> 1560. <hi>L. Cooke de jure div. Reg. Eccleſ. fol.</hi> 34.</note> I am ſure, would willingly authoriſe and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, provided that the King would grant him ſuch a <hi>Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> as muſt be granted him by ſuch, as ſay their <hi>Epiſcopall ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction</hi> is <hi>Iure Divino,</hi> and derive their calling from the Pope.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17436:4"/>
            <p>And becauſe this Biſhop conceived, that all other townes in the Kingdome, would follow the example of <hi>Edenb:</hi> hee comes therefore himſelfe into the <hi>Cathedrall Church,</hi> of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to have the ſaid <hi>booke</hi> there publiekly read: but it fell not out according to his expectation: for the people not being for merly tanght, that, that way and manner of <hi>Divine Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> which they had ever vſed from the reformaticn of that Church, was not fit nor lawfull, neither it ſtructed by the <hi>BB:</hi> that the <hi>Engliſh. Popiſh ſervice Booke</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">This all Reformed Churches tax us for; viz. that the <hi>Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>booke, is the Maſse,</hi> tranſlated into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh; and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt hit us for it in the teeth, ſaying that we are behoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them, for <hi>mattens and Evening ſong;</hi> &amp; this is known to our people gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, which makes their cauſe theworſe before God; in that they offer him ſuch a ſacrifice, as their conſcience tels them is an abomination.</note> was agreat deale better: nor being vſed to heare <hi>mattings</hi> and <hi>evening ſong,</hi> and <hi>ſinging ſervice:</hi> the <hi>Scotſmen</hi> I ſay not beeing uſed to ſuch <hi>geare,</hi> could not digeſt it: For they beleeved (and well they might,) that there was little difference between this <hi>booke worſhip</hi> and the Popes maſſe booke<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Scotſmen <hi>ſay very true, as appears by the words of</hi> K. Edward <hi>the ſixt;</hi> It ſeemes to you <hi>(ſayth he in his Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Rebels of the Weſt)</hi> that you have a new ſervice, novv indeed it is no other but the old, the ſelfe-ſame vvords in Engliſh vvhich are in Latin &amp;c If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſervice of the Church, vvas good in Lattin, it remaineth good in Engliſh for no thing is altered but to ſpeak with knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that vvhich vvas ignorantly <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uttered.</hi> Act and Monum. vol. <hi>2,</hi> pag. <hi>1497. 1498.</hi> Edit <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>, ſaving that the one is in Latine the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Engliſh.<note n="(c)" place="margin">
                  <hi>c Q uaer.</hi> Whether a <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſaying the <hi>Maſſe</hi> in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, and not underſtanding how fooliſh, falſe, and blaſphemous it is, doth not leſſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, then he that ſpeakes it in his owne tongue, and ſo knowes what hotch potch &amp; galle mawfry it is.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And howſoever the people generally, were greatly offended with the <hi>B.</hi> for this his bould attempt: yet the women<note n="(d)" place="margin">Let our Prelates look to it, leaſt when juſtice is not ſuffered to paſſe in an ordinary way, God raiſe not up other means, to execute his wrath upon them. The Dukes death may be a warning for them. <hi>Bloody and deceitfull men ſhall not live out halfe their dayes,</hi> Pſa. 55, 23. Let that <hi>Blood-thirſty murderous Butcher Laud</hi> thinke of the place.</note> not ſo well able as the men to forbeare open reſiſtance and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, roſe up without any ceremony, and droue the <hi>B:</hi> and <hi>Deane</hi> out of the Church:<note n="(e)" place="margin">I glad to ſee them whipt out, by the <hi>K. &amp; Parliam. ſe Pſa.</hi> 69:25.</note> ſome what like to our Saviours whipping the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple.</p>
            <p>The Biſhop being vexed, that he was thus <hi>women beaten,</hi> and the reſt of his brethren being no leſſe enrage thereat: what doe they now? they doe what they can, to ſet more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord between the King and his good ſubjects: and ſpecially they ſeeke to increaſe his wrath againſt the towne of <hi>Eden:</hi> thinking that all other townes in the land would be afliraid, to oppoſe any of the innovations, which they ſought to bring into that Church, if that city ſuffered ſome diſgrace at his Majeſties hands.</p>
            <p>And to accompliſh their wicked end this way, they procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red 1: a <hi>recommendation</hi> from his Majeſly vnto the <hi>town-coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill,</hi> to chuſe for a <hi>Proveſt</hi> or <hi>Major</hi> (he beeing dead that was before in place) one <hi>Hay,</hi> who had formerly ſerved under the <hi>Townclarke</hi> aman well acquainted with all the mercinarie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17436:5"/>wayes, that could bee vſed for working vpon that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and therefore the fitter man (as their <hi>Lordſhips</hi> thought) to bee choſen, for furthering the execution of their deepeplots and deſignes: being <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>deſignes,</hi> ſo contrary to, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>acts of Parliament, (Confeſſion of faith,</hi> and the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip of God</hi> in that Church: as they durſt not diſcover the ſame, to any one man, that was knowne to be honeſt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, or free from THAT CORRVPTION (you know what I meane) which that <hi>Hay</hi> for theſe many yeares, in the whole courſe of his life hath beene generally noted for. <hi>Novi Simonem &amp; Simon me:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. They procured a commandement from his Majeſtie, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Councill</hi> and <hi>Seſſion</hi> and all civill Courts of inſtice, that they ſhould depart from <hi>Eden:</hi> and ſit firſt at <hi>Lythgou</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards at Starling.<note n="(a)" place="margin">If there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to induce our <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>State,</hi> to hunt thoſe <hi>Vermins</hi> away; this were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; namely, their dayly attempts, to ſet ſtrife betweene them. Oh, that his majeſtie did ſee, how ungratefull they are this way to him; As <hi>Screetch-Ovvles,</hi> whiles they ſuck the <hi>Goats-milke</hi> doe marre the <hi>Vdder,</hi> So theſe never draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny benefit from Prin ces; But they wilbe fure (like unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Owles) to abuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for it if they can.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>unreaſonable men</hi> growing thus worſe and worſe. the better ſort at lenght of every condition and quality in the Kingdome, began to take the matter (as high time it was) home to heart:<note n="(b)" place="margin">We have more cauſe a great deale: conſidering what vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioſe and ſenceable miſeries the Land lies under by their meanes; Beſides, there is now a faire apportunity, offered to his Majeſtie, to free his three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes at once from the hurtfulſt plagues that they have. If ſome ſormer Kings of this Land, had ſecne the way ſo cleare, and the work ſo eaſie as now it is, they would ſoone have taken off their corner Caps, and ſet a Tyburn Tipper in the place there of.</note> and perceiving that vnleſſe there were ſome ſpeedie courſe taken, to take theſe <hi>little foxes</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Their Bb: may well be called <hi>Little Foxes,</hi> and <hi>ours</hi> the <hi>great Foxes,</hi> for in reſpect of villanie &amp; miſcheife, to ours, theirs, are no-bodies. Witnes <hi>Laud,</hi> who is more <hi>Fox wiſe</hi> then all the Bb. in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> and caſt them out <hi>head and tayle</hi> from the Lords Vineard,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Some may thinke that ſuch a worke wilbe difficult here with us, but I am otherwiſe minded. For theſe creatures are like nettles, which being ſoftly handled doe ſting, but if they are cruſt, the ſmart not, ſoe theſe are leaſt hurtfull when they are moſt cruſht.</note> there would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly come (and that ſoon) great preiudice to their religion, to the honour of their King and to to themſelves and their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, many wayes: They here upon perceiving I ſay (as men doe the raine in a black cloud) that ſenceable and viſible dangers lay at their dore, for prevention whereof, made choyſe of one or two of the graveſt Miniſters in every <hi>Preſbytery,</hi> &amp; one or two diſcreet gentlemen of every Shier, to preſent their complaints, remonſtrances and greviances to the <hi>Councill,</hi> that by their mediation and meanes, his Maieſty might be acquan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the ſame.</p>
            <p>Theſe Commiſioners upon <hi>Sept.</hi> 23 <hi>Oct.</hi> 15. and <hi>Decem.</hi> 7. &amp; 27. gave in vnto the Councill, ſuch ſupplications as were fit for his Maieſties information and ſpecially, that his ſubjects
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17436:5"/>feared<note n="(a)" place="margin">Our is more then a <hi>feare of innovation</hi> for wee have ſundry <hi>innovations</hi> eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among us, and the Prelates ſet their jornymen on vvork, to defend them; as <hi>Heylen, Reed, Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lington,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>Trencher Mates;</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his <hi>ungracious graceles Speech in the Star-Chamber.</hi>
               </note> an innovation in religion, wherby the common wealth was likely to ſuffer much.<note n="(b)" place="margin">They ſet us down a good patterne to follow; That is, to write up the wicked workes of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, and preſent them to his Majeſty; and I verelie thinke, if the King were rightly informed, what knowne Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors they are, to God to him, to the Land, and true Religion, and how deteſtable they are in the eyes of his people, and how much it doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienate his ſubjects affections from his Majeſty, that ſuch WORKERS OF INIQVITIE are ſuffered. I ſay if Majeſtie were thorowly poſſeſſed hereof, my mind gives me they ſhould not tarie in his ſight.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Biſhops perceiving that their <hi>workes of darkenese</hi> w now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to light &amp;, that the <hi>Commiſſioners</hi> taxed them, (&amp; that to true) for many treſonable aſſaults againſt their Religion eſtabliſhed by law, and many yeares peaceable profeſſed, and alſo for ſeeking by crafty wayes to bring into the Church, the <hi>rags</hi> and <hi>dregs</hi> of the <hi>Babilonian</hi> whore: the <hi>Bb:</hi> I ſay percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this, vſe meanes that the King, would referre all to the Councell, whereof themſelves were a great part: and truly this was no ſmall point of wiſedome in their Lordſhips, for they were not ſo blind, but they could ſee well enough, that unleſſe they themſelues might bee judges in their owne Caſe, they would bee judged by others to be <hi>Vnſavery ſalt and hence forth good for nothing, but to be cast out, and to be troden under foot.</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">What greater diſhonour can it be to our Nation, then to ſuffer ſuch in high and eminent places, who in the eſteeme of other Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are fitt only for the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And that there <hi>ravenous wolues</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">If the Church of Scotland doe ſo Iudge of them, then let them beware that they doe not upon any tearmes admitt of them againe. For wolves beeing kept a while from their prey, doe afterwards fall a devouring the more eagerlie and greedily, ſo will thoſe <hi>ſpirituall Wolves</hi> doe, if they can get againe into their places.</note>, might eſcape the hands of ſuch as were hunting after them, they procure (by whoſe meanes I know not) a <hi>Proclamation</hi> to bee publiſhed in <hi>Eden: ſebr:</hi> 19. 1638. wherein all the aforeſaid Commiſioners <hi>(the hunters of the Fox)</hi> were commanded vnder paine of treaſon to leaue the townes of <hi>Eden:</hi> and <hi>Starling,</hi> within ſix houres after the publication of the ſame: the words of the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are as followes.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17436:6"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARLES &amp;c.</hi> For ſo much as we out of our Princery care<note n="(a)" place="margin">If Princes will take care for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, they muſt doe then what the Word of God directeth the and not what <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Prelates</hi> (for their caſe, profitt, pleaſure, and ſuch worldly reſpects) perſwade them to doc. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.24 <hi>Gal.</hi> 4, 18.</note> of maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the true Religion all ready profeſſed, &amp; ſo beating downe all ſuperſtition: Having ordained a booke of common prayer to bee compiled for the generall and vniverſall uſe &amp; edification<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Hoccine credibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le aut memorabile.</hi> Will Satan caſt out Satan: He were an unwiſe man, that would bee perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the way to get light into his houſe, were by ſhutting his doorers &amp; windows; They that ſhould caſt aſide the true worſhip of Chriſt, and thinke to edifie themſelves better by uſing the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions <hi>ſervice-booke</hi> would ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were fooliſh:</note> of our ſubjects within our ancient King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Scotland, the ſame being accordingly don. In the framing whereof we tooke great care<note n="(c)" place="margin">I beleeve the <hi>Bb.</hi> tooke <hi>great care</hi> &amp; <hi>paines</hi> to have it as full of ſuperſtition as they could, but bleſſed be God, their labour was as vaine as their worke: and I hope <hi>the great care</hi> &amp; <hi>paines,</hi> that <hi>Laud</hi> and his <hi>Mates</hi> the Ieſuites now take, to bring in Poperie, will prove ſo to, that is the contrivers either forced to fly into other Countries, or hangd up at home for their treacherie and villanie.</note> &amp; paines, ſo that there is nothing paſt therein but was ſeen and approved by us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame was divulgated or printed: aſſuring all our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſubjects that not only our intention is, but even this very booke a ready meanes to maintaine the true Religion already profeſſed, and beat out all ſuperſtition, of which in our owne time we not doubt but in a faire courſe to ſatisfie the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our good ſubjects: But having ſeen and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome petitions and declarations given into our counſell againſt the ſaid Booke, and late CANNONS of the booke, find our regall authority much iniured thereby, both in the matter and the carrage, whereby wee certifie theſe of the Nobility, Gentry, Barrons Miniſters and others who have keept and aſſiſted thoſe meetings and convocations for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving and ſubſcribing of the ſaid petitions, to be liable<note n="(d)" place="margin">Better that men <hi>cenſured us</hi> for well dooing, then that Chriſt in the laſt day, ſhould paſſe ſentence of condemnation againſt us, for yeelding unto their unjuſt demaunds.</note> to our cenſure, in their perſons and fortunes, they having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyned themſelves without conſent or authority: Yet becauſe wee beleeve that they have done herein only out of a prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous zeale, and without diſloyalty or diſaffection in our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraingty: Our gracious pleaſure (ſo farr as concernes thoſe metings for conſulting and ſubſcription of the ſaid petitions or preſenting of the ſame to any judges of this Kingdom) is to diſpence therewith, and with what may bee the fault or error therein, to all ſuch as upon ſignfication or declaration of this our pleaſure, ſhall retaine themſelves as become good and dutifull ſubjects.<note n="(e)" place="margin">As the 3 <hi>Nobles in Daniel</hi> were the Kings <hi>good and dutifull ſubjects,</hi> albeit they bowed not before the <hi>image;</hi> So are the <hi>Nobilitie, Gentry</hi> &amp; <hi>Miniſters</hi> in Scotland, good &amp; dutifull ſubjects, although they refuſe the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-booke: Yea to ſay the truth they are better ſubjects to his Majeſtie, then ſuch as conforme to it here in England.</note> To which purpoſe OVR WILL is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17436:6"/>henceforth, and we charge you ſtraghtly and commaund, that incontinetly theſe our letters ſeene, the particulers in our name &amp; authority proclamation therof be made to all our leige ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in all places needfull; that ſoe none pretend ignorance hereof, and therewithall <hi>in our name and authoroty</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">It is no new thing for Princes, by the inſtigation of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Prelates, to have their <hi>names and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> abuſed; I has was <hi>Conſiantines au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> abuſed, when he authorized by the perſwaſion of <hi>Bb.</hi> the <hi>Arrian Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie.</hi> So <hi>Theodeſius</hi> when he eſtabliſhed the Haereſie of <hi>Entiches;</hi> So <hi>Arcedins</hi> when hee baniſhed Chriſoſtome.</note> that ye diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge charge all ſuch convocations<note n="(b)" place="margin">The way for his Majeſtie to have ſuch <hi>convocations</hi> &amp; <hi>meetings diſcharged;</hi> is to diſcharge the Bb. of their power and places, and in his <hi>name</hi> &amp; <hi>authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> to call a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and willingly to ſuffer a legall pro ceeding againſt the Prelates; and in this God ſhall have gle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the King honour, the Land peace, and the enemies of the Lord their due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, and untill this be, neither England nor Scotland wil ſee good dayes.</note> &amp; meetings in time to come, vnder the penalty of <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and alſo that ye command, charge and inhibit our leiges and ſubjects, that none of them on any hand preſume to reſort or repaire to the Burrough of Starling, nor to any other Burrough, where our counſell and Seſſion ſits, till firſt they declare the cauſe of their comming to our counſell, and declare their warrant to that effect. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that wee command and charge all and Sundrie <hi>Provoſts, Bayleives,</hi> and <hi>Magistrates</hi> within their Burroughs that they and every one of them have a ſpeciall care and regard, to ſee this our <hi>Royall will</hi> and <hi>pleaſure</hi> readily and dutifully obſerved in all points, and that no violence bee ſuffered within your bounds, under all the higheſt penalty, crime or offence that they may commit againſt us in that behalfe: And alſo that ye commaund and charge all and ſundry <hi>Noblemen Barrons</hi> &amp; <hi>Burgeſſes</hi> who are not actually indwellers within the Burrough neither are of number of the privy counſell and Seſſion, and members therof, and are already within this Burrough: that they and euery one of them remoue themſelves, and depart and paſſe forth of the ſaid Burrough (and not returne againe without the ſaid warrant) within Six houres after the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation hereof, <hi>vnder the ſaid penalty of Treaſon:</hi>
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">It is high time for the Nobilitie both in Scotland &amp; England to looke about them, conſidering the monſtrous unparaled preſumption of Bb. who are growne ſo impudent, as they are not affraid to perſwade Kings, to proclaime all the great Peeres and Princes of the Land, Traitors &amp; Rebels, if they will not become the which uſed to bite people, and howſoever he was ſpoken often unto of it, yethee refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it not; At laſt the curre wounded the man himſelfe &amp; his Children; at this he was very angry and cauſed the curre to be hanged immediately. We poore men have been a long time biten by the <hi>Prelaticall Dogs,</hi> and we have complained thereof to your Honours but you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> And as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any petitions that ſhall hereafter be given to vs upon this or any otner Subject: wee are likewiſe pleaſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that wee will not ſhut our cares there from: Soe it bee not prejudiciall to our royall authority. <hi>Given at Starling vnder our Signet</hi> the 19 of Febr: 1638.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Per actum Dominorum Conſily.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17436:7"/>
            <p>For the ſafety of religion, the honour of the King, and the lawfull liberties and previledges of the ſubjects, the Nobility and Commiſſioners aforeſaid, were forced to publiſh a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation againſt the Proclamation: and thus they ſay.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE Noble men,<note n="(a)" place="margin">It is a thing to bee wiſhed, that our No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen, Barens and Miniſters, would take to heart, the greevances of the time, and joyntly ſeek by a lawful way the redreſſe thereof. We ſee in Worldly matters, what one cannot doe, many can; So in this caſe, howſoever ſome few ſingle men, have not prevailed with the King, to eaſt out the bond-woman &amp; her children, yet if there be a general ſeeking by the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there is no fear but he will give a gracious anſwere.</note> Barrons and Miniſters ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to attend his <hi>Majeſties</hi> anſwer vnte our humble petitions, and to preſent our gree uances and to doe what elſe might lawfully conduce to our humble deſires. Did upon the 13. of <hi>September</hi> laſt, preſent one ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to your <hi>Lordſhips;</hi> and another upon <hi>October</hi> following: as alſo a new relatiue to the former in <hi>December</hi> after the 19. day.</p>
                  <p>In all which wee humbly remonſtrated, our iuſt exceptions againſt the <hi>Service book,</hi> &amp; <hi>booke of Cannons, Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhips</hi> of this Kingdom, as the contrivers,<note n="(b)" place="margin">They may wel be called <hi>contrivers;</hi> for I know not, for what uſe they are in all the world, unleſſe it bee to contrive wayes, how to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; to advance Antichriſt.</note> meanteaners &amp; urgers thereof; &amp; againſt their ſitting as our Judges<note n="(c)" place="margin">When will theeves, murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp;c. be puniſhed if none, but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves may judge their cauſe. Might the Bb. be brought to an impartiall triall, no doubt but they would be ſoone condemned, for notorious malefactors; But if their facts may not be examined any where, but where they themſelves are Iudges, it wilbe long enought before they ſuffer according to their merit.</note> until the cauſes betweene them and us bee decided.</p>
                  <p>And withall wee earneſtly ſuplicated to beeridd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe evils,<note n="(d)" place="margin">If the <hi>Scotſmen</hi> have juſt cauſe,, to ſeeke his Majeſtie, that they may be <hi>rid</hi> of Bb. and their <hi>Tayle.</hi> What cauſe have we then, to ſeeke for it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving beene a thouſand ſould more baſely abuſed by them, then ever they were; Truely it is to be wondered that we are ſtill; but it may be our Nation forbeares to petition his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> in earneſt</note> &amp; from all other innovations of that kind, introducted againſt the laudable lawes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: as namely that of the <hi>High Commiſſion</hi> and other evils particularly and generally mentioned in our lupplications &amp; complaints: And that theſe our <hi>Parties,</hi> delinquent againſt our religion and lawes might be taken order with, and theſe preſſing greeuiances bee redreſſed, according to the Lawes of this Realme, as in our ſupplications wee have more largely expreſſed, the which wee gave unto your Lordſhips upon the <hi>19. December</hi> aforeſaid, againſt the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops our <hi>parties,</hi> who by conſequence therefore neither could be, nor may be our Iudges.</p>
                  <p>Whereupon your Lordſhips declared by your act given at <hi>Dealkieth</hi> the ſaid 19 of <hi>December,</hi> that you would preſent our Petition to his Majeſtie Royall conſideration, and that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17436:7"/>without any prejudice to us the ſaid <hi>Supplicants,</hi> and moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that wee ſhould bee heard,<note n="(a)" place="margin">It is a crying none of this Land, that the poore mans cry is not heard; And this comes to paſſe, through the craſt of Prelates, who ſeeke to have their cauſes juſtified in all Courts without any triall or examination. If a <hi>Bat</hi> touch a <hi>Storkes</hi> egge, it becomes (they ſay) addle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I know not what the ſecret operation is, that Bb. have in their <hi>touch:</hi> But this I know, by their <hi>touch</hi> they make many <hi>addle egges,</hi> or rather <hi>addle heads</hi> both in Church and Common-wealth.</note> in time and place conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and in the meane time we ſhould receaue no prejudice as the ſaid act it ſelfe teſtifies for us.</p>
                  <p>Now whereas wee your ſupplicants (with long patitence and hope grounded upon ſundry promiſes) were exſpecting an anſwere unto our fore named humble deſires, wee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of ſome direction from his Majeſtie, to your Lords of his highnes privy counſell, touching our complaints: and upon the ſame addmitted the conſulting and iudging<note n="(b)" place="margin">If the <hi>Nobilitie, Barons,' Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their cauſe upon the Kings Commaundement to the Bb. their Church had not been ſo ſoone pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of <hi>Romiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</hi> And for our parts, unleſſe with the <hi>Noole Scots</hi> we refuſe to admitt them for our Iudges, we ſhall never ſhake them of with their <hi>ſpirituall whoredoms.</hi>
                     </note> both, of our ſupplication, and the Kings anſwere there to, vnto the <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> our direct <hi>par-ties:</hi> Contrary to our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation given at <hi>Dealkeeth,</hi> and ſince renued at <hi>Starling:</hi> and contrary to your Lordſhips foreſaid act<note n="(c)" place="margin">It much impeacheth the honour and reputation of <hi>Stateſmen,</hi> to comply with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates; For howſoever they hould up their heads, looke bigge upon the matter, &amp; Bleſſe themſelves; yet, by good &amp; bad, they are hated all the Land over, and it is a received <hi>Maxime</hi> among the people, that <hi>he cannot be honeſt, and be for the Biſhopes.</hi> If a Horſe chance to ſteppe in the track of a Wolfe, he is made lame by it. Theſe <hi>Wolves</hi> have the like ſtrange operation, for whoſoever comes into their way, he halts for ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> made at <hi>Dealkeeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Leaſt therefore our ſilence ſhould bee prejudiciall to this ſoe importunate a cauſe, as concernes Gods Glory and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, our Religion and Salvation, the lawes and Liberties of this Kingdome: or derogatory to our former ſupplications and complaints: or in briefe, not anſwerable to the truſt of our commiſſion: wee are forced out of our bounden duty to God, our <hi>King</hi> and natiue Country to take inſtrument in the no taries and <hi>Clarkes</hi> hands (ſeeing your Lordſhips refuſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our Declimiter for remouall of theſe of our <hi>parties</hi>) and to proteſt in manner following.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Wee proteſt that wee may, and ought to have a imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate courſe to preſent our iuſt greeviances to our ſacred So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verainge, and in a legall way and manner to proſecute the ſame, before the ordinarie competent judges, Civill or Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall: without any offence either offred by us, or taken by your Lordſhips.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We proteſt that the <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> the <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> whome wee complaine vpon, cannot bee reputed or eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med lawfull iudges, to ſit in iudicatory within this Kingdome Civill or Eccleſiaſticall, upon any of us the ſaid ſupplicants:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17436:8"/>untill they doe by lawfull tryall iuditiouſly purge themſelves of ſuch crimes as wee have already laid to their Charge: offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſelves to prove the ſame whenſoever his Majeſty ſhal be pleaſed to give vs audience.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Wee proteſt that no act<note n="(a)" place="margin">Our Land would be happie, if it were free from the <hi>unjuſt acts</hi> and <hi>Cenſures</hi> of Orelates; For trulie <hi>Iſrael</hi> never ſighed more, under the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian bondage,</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the better ſort, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rywhere cry out &amp; complaine of their oppreſſion and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie. It may be they thinke, that our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences (like Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Shouldiers) are ſtrong enought to beare all the loads they lay upon us. But our State hath learned now of Scot land, how to bee eaſed of their burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </note> or proclamation, whether paſd or here after ſhall paſſe, in the counſell, and by the ſtates of <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> (our <hi>par-ties</hi> and whome we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyned to be our Iudges) ſhall in no wiſe be preiudicall to us, that is, either to our perſons, or lawfull meetings, proceedings and perſuits.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We proteſt that neither our ſelves, nor any others,<note n="(b)" place="margin">It is a ſweet <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony</hi> when me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> joyn together in good actions; Certainly were there ſuch an accord among the <hi>Nobilitie, Barons, Miniſters,</hi> &amp;. her e in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. It vvould make theſe proud <hi>Nimrods</hi> harts to quake: For their hope of ſtanding, is in regard of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in the <hi>Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Miniſters,</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> but my minde gives me, God vvill put it into their hearts ſhortly, to ſhevv the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Scots trick</note> whoſe hearts the Lord ſhall moue to joyne with vs in our ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the aforeſaid innovations, ſhall incurre any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, either in life, lands, or any politicall or Eccleſiaſticall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie: For not obſerving ſuch acts, Bookes, Cannons, Writs, judicatories and proclamations introduced without, or againſt the acts of Parliament, or ſtatutes of this Kingdome. But it ſhal be lawfull for us and them to uſe our ſelves in matters of Religion,<note n="(c)" place="margin">The <hi>Scots</hi> Nation is vvorthy of honour above many Nations; For that in Religion, they have not beene the Servants of men, neither follovved their Kings, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thervviſe then their Kings have followed Chriſt. Contrariwiſe it is the ſhame &amp; blott of our Nation, that in matters of Gods worſhip, we are as our Princes are, and ready to turne and change as they doe, and what doth this argue, but that men ſerve not the Lord Ieſus, but their owne bellies.</note> or the externall worſhip of God, and policie of the Church; according to the word of God, and the laudable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, of this Church and Kingdome.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Seeing all ſuch as have taken theſe innovations to heart, have by a legall &amp; ſubmiſſiue way of ſupplications ſought re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, and beene calme and quiet in hope of reformation: We proteſt therefore that if inconvenience ſhall happen to fall out (which wee pray God to prevent) upon the preſſing of the ſaid innouations or evils, generally and ſpecially mentioned in our former complaints, and upon your Lordſhips refuſall, to take order for redreſſe. That the ſame ſhall not bee impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto vs, who moſt humbly deſire to have all things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed by order.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Wee proteſt before God, the Heavens, and the Angles, that theſe our Requeſt (proceding from conſcience, and our due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect to his Majeſties honour) doe tend to no other end, but to the preſervation of the true reformed religion, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17436:8"/>Lawes and Liberties of his Majeſties moſt ancient Kingdome and the ſatisfaction of our humble deſires contained in our ſupplications, according to his Majeſties goodneſſe and juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice; From whom we do certainly exſpect,<note n="(a)" place="margin">What they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, appeares by their petitions and complaints; viz. the exerciſe of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all Popiſh ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, &amp; a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to arraigne the Bb. upon the <hi>crime of Innovations.</hi> And I beleeve that theſe things, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie will grant them. The which if he doe, then I doubt not, but our Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, Barons, and Miniſters will ſue to his Majeſtie for the like grant, that ſo this way, and not in Antichriſts way, there may be a uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity betweene the two Kingdoms.</note> that his Maj. wil proceed &amp; grant remedy to our iuſt petitions &amp; complaints, as may be exſpected from ſo gracious a King towards his loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and dutifull Subjects, calling for redreſſe of ſo oppreſſing greevances, praying hartily that his Majeſty may long &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſly raigne over us. AMEN</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>THis proteſtation beeing publiſhed, the Prelates here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at were ſo daunted, as their courage began to faile<note n="(b)" place="margin">So will the hearts faile of our Bb. if the <hi>State</hi> deale roundly with them; For they may be well compared to the <hi>Crocodile,</hi> who is feirce and terrible to ſuch as feare her, &amp; run from her; But of no courage in ſtanding out againſt ſtrong oppoſtion. Or rather like the Aſſe, that wrapt himſelfe in the Lyons ſkin, and marched a farre of, to ſtrike terrour in the hearts of the Beaſts, but when the Fox drew neere, he not only perceived his long ears, but likewiſe diſcovered him, &amp; made him a jeſt to all the Beaſts of the forreſt.</note> them, &amp; what to doe, they know not; for they perceive that their <hi>Kingdome of Darknes,</hi> is now falling<note n="(c)" place="margin">Miſe perceiving that the Houſe wherin they are, is about to fall, do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contently leave the place; Theſe Bb. ſhewed the wit of a <hi>Mouſe,</hi> in running away in time, and for my part I cannot blame them much for it, neither would be very ſory, if ours would doe ſo too, conſidering they know that their cauſe is ſo ill, as they cannot with comfort ſtay, and ſuffer for it.</note> and out they muſt. Hereupon ſome of them ſecretly fled away into England, and theſe <hi>poore hearts,</hi> being full of greefe, uſed ſundry epiſcopall meanes, or <hi>antidotes</hi> to expell the venemous deſeaſe, which they brought with them from <hi>Scotland;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other choſe helpes (as fitting beſt their place and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) two or three of them, made themſelves ſtarke drunke; and in one night, brake 12: or 14: dozen of venice glaſſes, in drinking healths over and over, to the confuſion of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17436:9"/>
            <p>Others of them in the mean time, imployed themſelves in the affaires of their ſtate, and craued his Majeſties ayd and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and to prevaile this way, they made greevious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt the <hi>Scotts,</hi> and perſwaded the King to take up armes againſt them,<note n="(a)" place="margin">The Peaſt <hi>Duron</hi> perceiving her ſelfe almoſt take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, avoyds a great deal of dung thinking by the noy ſomnes thereof, to hinder the hunters from following her. This filthy ſhift dee the Bb. uſe, for when they ſee that the <hi>State</hi> hath almoſt eatch them, they ſeeke to eſeape, by avoiding their dung; that is, ſecrerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting to the King, many lies and vile ſlaunders againſt the hunters of them.</note> for ſeeing faire meanes would not doe it, fowl meanes might: moreover they would perſwade him, that it could not ſtand with his honour &amp;<note n="(b)" place="margin">I know not any Honour or good Service, that ever his Majeſty had by them; but rather Ioſſe &amp; prejudice; for as the ivie claſpes the oake, only to ſuck out ſap from it, for her leaves &amp; her ries; ſo theſe ſeeke to be in Princes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, only thereby to rayſe themſelves, and for nothing elſe.</note> ſafety to ſuffer<note n="(c)" place="margin">The finer parts being ſevered from the groſſer, there followes clearenes, ſweetnes, purenes, &amp;c. So when our Land is once purged from the infection of the Prelacie, both King and Subjects will doe the better after.</note> that Kingdome to bee without <hi>Bb.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Great joy<note n="(d)" place="margin">The like cauſe of rejoycing the Lord ſend to England. For I am ſure they have occaſioned ſorrow &amp; greife to her theſe many yeares.</note> there was in <hi>Scotland</hi> when they heard the <hi>Bite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheepes</hi> had left them: and the ſaying every where was: <hi>The Lord hath don great things for vs.</hi> And now they found that true in <hi>Prav.</hi> and that in the <hi>Poes-</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Venit post multos vnaſerenae dies.</q>
            <p>And becauſe they reſolved, to keepe peace<note n="(e)" place="margin">Our Prelates are like <hi>Nahaſh the Ammonite,</hi> who would not be at peace with <hi>Iabeſh, Gilead,</hi> unleſſe he might truſt out all their right eyes; So they cannot abide any man, neither will have accord with him, but perſecute him to the death; Who will not ſinne againſt knowedge &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in yeelding to their <hi>filthy baggage</hi> &amp; <hi>traſh.</hi>
               </note> with holines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, they tooke counſell what was beſt to bee don for the effecting hereof. If was at laſt by mutially conſent agreed vpon, to renew their ancient Covenant with God, &amp; one with another, the which band or Covenant being compoſed, it was generally ſubſcribed too, by all the better ſort in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>And as I have heard, one maine reaſon wherefore they were ſo carefull to take ſuch a courſe as the <hi>Prelates</hi> ſhould no more come among them, was in regard they ſaw ſuch cruelty and baſeneſe, in the <hi>Engliſh Bb.</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">Such is there baſenes, that they are ſpoken of everywhere; and in truth, ſorraigne nations doe admire, that ſo generous a nation as the Engliſh can ſuffer ſuch <hi>Dunghill Wormes,</hi> to exerciſe the crueltie that they doe over them. But I beleeve England will vindicate her Honour ſhortly this way, and like Scotland will drive away theſe <hi>Locuſts</hi> from her Coaſt; And then it will truely be ſaid of both Kingdomes, what is commonly ſaid: <hi>Great Brittaine the moſt renovvne and famous Ile in the World.</hi>
               </note> for ſaid they, howſoever he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, <hi>Ours</hi> have not don ſo wickedly as they: yet who knowes what they may doe in time: therefore it is good to keepe them out whiles they are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Confeſſion followes.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17436:9"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Covenant</hi> beeing made, and order given for ſubſcription to it throughout the Land; the Bb. hereat reged beyond meaſure. And like <hi>Athaliah</hi> cryed out <hi>Treaſon Treaſon:</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">The Prelates are like him, who beeing only guilty of follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: Yet in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuru cries out as main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly as he can, <hi>ſtop the theefe, ſtop the theefe,</hi> not caring who is apprehended, ſo himſelfe may eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape without daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: So they, howl it the <hi>Arch traitors,</hi> to God and the King, notwithſtaning are ſo impudent, as to chardge others with ſuch crimes, as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only are guilty of.</note> And becauſe they ſaw it was in vaine for them to uſe the courſes which they had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; <hi>viz.</hi> of ſilencing, baniſhing, impriſoning, fining, &amp;c. (for no man now would be ſo uſed by them<note n="b" place="margin">We doe much diſhonour the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to obey any of the <hi>Bb. Articles, Canons, Cenſures, &amp;c.</hi> the ſame beeing againſt Gods Law and Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. Bur rather ſtand faſt (as the <hi>brave Scots</hi>) in our Chriſtian Libertie, and ſay to thoſe <hi>workers of iniquitie,</hi> (as Chriſt will ſay one day to them) <hi>depart yee curſed of the Lord, we know you not.</hi>
                  </note> they be ganne to make ojbections againſt the Covenant, as thus.<note n="(c)" place="margin">If the Prelates could not helpe themſelves mere by their <hi>Purſevants Iayles Pillaries, &amp;c.</hi> then they can by disputation: as no man now loves them, ſo then no bodie woald feare them: For aſſoon may a man perſwade ihem to hang themſelves in their Courts, as to reaſon by the Word of God, with any godly man that comes before them. All their abilitie lies in this terrible argument: <hi>Take him away Jaylor.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. They produce an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> An. 1585. which prohibited all <hi>leagues</hi> and bands made by ſubjects without the Kings conſent, under paine as beeing holden and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as movers of Sedition, and ſuch is this Covenant and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription.</p>
               <p>to this it is anſwered. 1. Seeing the band and union is for the maintenance of true Religion, the Kings Authoritie and Lawes, and for the publick welfaire and peace of the whole Realme, againſt ſuch as ſeeke the ruine thereof; It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſtly tear med ſuch a league among ſubjects, as by the foreſaid act is prohibited.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Ours is no private band of ſome particular perſons, but a publick one, of the collective bodie of the whole Land; Now, it may not be thought, that they who made the Act, intended to prohibite themſelves from entering into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, and for God and the King.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This is no band againſt Law, but a renuing only of a <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> which <hi>King lames</hi> authorized both by proclamation and his practice too.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17436:10"/>
               <p>But admitt there were ſome inform alitie in it, in regard they craved not his Majeties conſent before they made the Covenant; Notwithſtanding <hi>(rebus ſic stantibus)</hi> conſidering to what extreame miſeries<note n="(a)" place="margin">What <hi>Mariners</hi> a caſe either they can not crane the maiſters ayd, or if they craue it, cannot optaine it, I ſay in ſuch a caſe, what mariners will not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour, to preſerve the veſſel from drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, rather then ſit ſtill, &amp; ſo maiſter &amp; men peeriſh toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I leaue the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the wiſe reader</note> many wayes the Bb. had brought them, it was as neceſſarie and lawfull for them to doe wnat they did, for the good of the Church; as was <hi>Heſters</hi> approaching to <hi>King Aſſuerus,</hi> before he held out his goul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Scepter, made neceſſarie and lawfull by reaſon of the eminent daunger that they were in, through <hi>Hammous</hi> ſuggeſtion to the King.</p>
               <p>Another thing objected by the Adverſarie is, that all ſuch as ſubſcribe to this Covenant, oblidge themſelves to practice ſuch things, as by the act of <hi>Perth Aſſembly</hi> was appointed to be uſed.</p>
               <p>To this they anſwer. 1. For <hi>Perth Aſsembly,</hi> they ſay as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Councill</hi> he'd at Ariminum, <hi>illud ago concilium exhorreo.</hi> That Convocation was not Lawfull: For the moderators and other members thereof, were not rightly choſen. Againe, the carriages of all buſineſſes went by craft and guile,<note n="(b)" place="margin">After ſuch a manner are their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations brought into the Engliſh Church that is, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>craft</hi> or <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> or both. For the <hi>Bb.</hi> know, that they are ſo wel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved in England, that it is not poſſible that any thing ſhould be don for their meantenance, in a faire &amp; legall way. As Wolves take the advantage of the darke night, for to kill &amp; deuour the Sheepe: ſo theſe Wolves, make uſe of in juſtice &amp; violence for to praey upon Chriſte poore lambes.</note> and not legallie and impartially, Beſides, ſeeing their cheife pretence for the introduction of <hi>genu-cultus</hi> then ordained, was becauſe the memory of ſuperſtition was paſt. It muſt follow that they who forbeare the practice, have as good, or rather a better reaſon for it; Namelie, becauſe the practice of it will revive thememory of ſuperſtition.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, it is well knowne, that ſundry of the innovations concluded <hi>at Perth,</hi> have not been by the Prelates themſelves yet practiſed;<note n="(c)" place="margin">Howſoever the Prelates doe preſſe conformitie: yet it muſt not be thought that they doe it of any conſcience: but they invent certaine <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> Canons, <hi>Articles,</hi> &amp;c. Unto which they thinke no honeſt man will ſubſcribe: &amp; ſo hope, by keeping out all able &amp; faithfull men from the miniſterie, &amp; giving others juſt occaſion to leaue their Churches, they hope (I ſay) in a little time, to bring the whole nation to be <hi>Atheſts</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> &amp; they (omnia ſamilia) as <hi>birds of a feather,</hi> they will agree well enought.</note> Now, by the ſame reaſon and ground that they omitt ſome of <hi>thoſe innovations,</hi> the ſubſcribers may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare the practice both of them and the others alſo; And the rather ſeeing moſt Churches<note n="(d)" place="margin">As the <hi>Lyon</hi> (in the Greek fable) would needs have the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> and fox to be of his Councill: becauſe he knew they would doe any thing that he ſhould command them, ſo the <hi>Bb.</hi> place abroad in the pariſh Churches of the Land, either <hi>Knaves</hi> or <hi>Fooles:</hi> for they know, that ſuch fellowes like (Foxes &amp; Aſſes) will doe any thing at their cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund: I ſay any thing, ſo that it be for advantage. As that lewd fellow profeſſeth in the poet, <hi>Dorio</hi> the <hi>Baud: non pudet vanitatis: minime, dum ad rem:</hi> Had we ſuch</note> in the Kingdome, have not to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17436:10"/>this day acknowledged, the things there concluded, for the conſtitutions of a lawfull aſſembly.</p>
               <p>It is further objected, that <hi>Perth Aſſembly</hi> was ratified by an <hi>Act of Parliament Ann.</hi> 1621. and therefore the <hi>Subſcribers</hi> obleidge themſelves to forbeare to practice that which by Parliament they are commaunded to practice.</p>
               <p>To anſwer it, 1. <hi>Parliamentarie Ratifications,</hi> can no way al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Church Canons,</hi> concerning the worſhip of God; For it beeing but a Counſell, the <hi>Parliament</hi> cannot turne it into a precept; No more then it can change precepts into Counſels, For that were rather to make Lawes and Canons in matters of Religion then to confirme them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There are no commanding words in the ratification, which can ſimplie bind, the greater and better ſort of ſubjects, to a literall obedience of the Articles made in that aſſimbly: the reaſon is, becauſe there was a ſupplication given to the members of that Parliament, before they ſate, that they would be pleaſed to heare ſuch grounds and reaſons, as ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to them againſt the ratification of Perth Aſſembly. Moreover when the <hi>Supplicators</hi> were ſuppreſd, they made their proteſtation in due time and place according to order of law. Beſides his Majeſty Commiſſioners in that Parliament ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly promiſed, never to preſſe<note n="(a)" place="margin">They have had more fauour ſhewen them, then we have had: for <hi>Ceremonic</hi> here are ſo vrged, as that the Omiſſion of them; is more ſeve relie puniſhed, the the breach of any law of God: yea the truth is, ſo men we be, <hi>Ceremoniouſh ſupeſtitious.</hi> It is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the religion the Bb care or and it is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> much religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the have themſelves.</note> the execution of the act, no penalty ſhould bee exacted, and that there ſhould not be any further of conformity to the Engliſh Ceremenies: in ſhort the a foreſaid <hi>Subſcribers</hi> have proteſted againſt iuriſdiction of Prelates, and inparticular againſt their high Commiſſion,<note n="(b)" place="margin">The City of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> nouriſhed the grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bird <hi>this</hi> to deno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> garbage &amp; offall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it, and to cleanſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtreets; but he left <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> his own fithines at beaſlines mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> noyſome behind him the high <hi>Comiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Court</hi> is allowed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pretence cleanſe the hand the <hi>Offals</hi> of ſinn but the truth is, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it doth not: but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther like that b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> voyds ſo much du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; filthines as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the whole Kingdome is annoyed therewith our ſtate therfore ſhall doe wel to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> downe this <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Baal,</hi> &amp; (as loſiah did the <hi>houſe of the Sodomites</hi>) turne it to a <hi>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> or draught-houſe, and ſo it ſhall keepe ſtill its nature and kind.</note> and all other their Courts, Canons, Articles, and proceedings.</p>
               <p>no doubt but theſe, and other ſuch like objections, were ſuggeſted to his Majeſtie, &amp; ſeing he heard not the anſers<note n="(c)" place="margin">Princes ſhould be like the ſunne, which caſteth her ſhining beemes upon all a like his Majeſtie wilbe pleaſed to receine <g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>our charges &amp; proofes againſt the <hi>Bb.</hi> in as f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and favourable a way: as he doth their charges without preffe againſt us we doubt but to make it cleare, yea and his Majeſtie ſhall conſeld it, that they are neither fitt Church or Common wealth.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">d It hath been the overthrow of maine brave princes, to take things upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the reporter: for by this meanes diſſentions have fallen out between them their beſt ſubjects, &amp; here upon, treacherous men (as the Prelats are) have taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> time &amp; advantage to hurt both parnies.</note>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17436:11"/>it is poſſible he might be offended with his beſt ſubjects: ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering, that his Majeſty hath things preſented to him, in ſuch ſhapes and lineaments as the Prelates conceive to to bee moſt for their owne ends and advantages. notwill ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch was his Maiſties wiſdome and loue to his ancient Subjects, as that he refuſed to attempt the actions which ſome perſwaded him unto.<note n="(a)" place="margin">What Prelates are, the Spun of God ſhoweth in <hi>Rev. 16.13. viz. the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean pirits which goe unto the Kings of the hearth, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them to battle againſt the Saints.</hi> Now, as Aliad bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing encouraged by his falſe Prephers, to goe againſt <hi>Raniath Gilead,</hi> was undone by it: So many in mking the Bb. coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to warre againſt the Gespell, have been undone by the meanes, in their state honour, poſteritie.</note> But ſent the <hi>Mar:</hi> of <hi>Ham:</hi> down into Scotland, to heare what they could ſay for themſelves: &amp; how they could juſtifie the band they had made and So to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his Majeſtie how all things ſtood: And no doubt but his Maieſtie did this the rather as conceaving in his royall breaſt, that it was not poſſible, that ſo many of his beſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and men of the greateſt integrity and prudence, would have agreed together in an action of ſuch a nature without Some conſiderable reaſon and cauſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Marques</hi> being come into <hi>Eden:</hi> much ſpeech paſſed between him and the commiſſioners for the Land: they craved the indiction of a free Aſlembly and Parliament, as the only remeady of their miſeries: hee required a rendring up of the whole copies of the <hi>Subſcribed Covenant</hi> telling them that this would bee a meanes to remove all feares of the <hi>Kings</hi> wrath againſt the ſubſcribers and If they refuſed to doe ſoe, the King:<note place="margin">b The ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy we crave here in England; the which being granted, we feaoe not that but Church and Common-wealth, ſhall be both the better for it. What Children ſeeing Serpents creeping in their Fathers and Mothers boſome, will not kill them to preſerve their Parents: Thoſe Bb. as ſo many venemous ſnakes, lie in the boſome (as it were) of our <hi>Abimelech Father King</hi> and of the Church; Now, the Parliament-men as good Children will kill thoſe Serpents, that ſo both Father and Mother may live and proſper.</note> (it might by) would not grant them an affemblie or parliament, for eſtabliſhing religion, and ſetling the Peace of Kirk and Kingdome.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17436:11"/>
               <p>But they anſwered that thus they could not doe, for if they ſhould they ſhould not bee free of the great guiltines of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uirie before God:<note n="(a)" place="margin">Note the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes of our Bb: it is their order to have infams in baptiſine, to vow and promiſe by their <hi>ſureties</hi> to <hi>fight againct the devil &amp; al his vvorkes.</hi> yet afterwards, they doe what they can, to make them perinted &amp; foreſworne in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them, to fight for the Devil &amp; his workes: that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> for them and the Pope.</note> Againe in this they ſhould deſtroy what they had before built &amp; confeſſe themſelves to be treſpaſſers, bfore they ſaw it beſides they ſhould ſhew great unthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes vnto God, for a worke which by his good ſpirit they were moved to doe. Moreover the demaund was more then the Commiſſioners could doe, in regard many thouſands in the Land beſides themſelves had ſubſcribed: To be ſhort, they ſaid, and that truely, if they ſhould grant this, all the World would wonder at their inconſtancy, and their enemies would mock at them, and traduce them, as periured Covenant-breakers, and Troublers of the peace of the Kirk and Kingdome. And whereas there were many promiſes made of great matters that the King would doe for them: if they would render up the Copies to him. Their anſwere was: that this was not the firſt time,<note n="(b)" place="margin">It is the property of the fox to come towards the ſheep upon his bellie, &amp; to ſhew him ſelfea farre off, as if he meant no harme; but being gotten with in them and where he would be: then like a fox he kils &amp; ſpares not ſo the <hi>Prelates,</hi> till they become where they defire to be, they are very freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; full of faire promiſes, but having gotten what they ſeeke for, then like ſoxes as they are they ſpoile ane devour the Lords ſheep.</note> that fair promiſes had beene made them: for not vrging of of Articles already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, and for not trouble them with any further innovation the which beeing credited, did enſnare manie and drew them on to doe that, which otherwiſe they would not have don: all which promiſes have beene broken and denyed, when the per formance was craved, and why may they not exſpect the like in this caſe, eſpecially where the thing wilbee found more hard and difficult.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17436:12"/>
               <p>There beeing much time ſpent, and no concluſion made of any thing, at the laſt there comes downe a <hi>Proclamation</hi> from the King. The which was probliſhed at the <hi>Mercate Croſse</hi> of <hi>Edinburg</hi> the 4 of <hi>July</hi> 1638. the effect whereof was this. That his Majeſtie was <hi>not ignorant of their great deſorders</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">If there be diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders among them, the greateſt ault lies on the <hi>Proclates</hi> who have been the cheife Authors and cauſers of it. And therefore his Majeſtie ſhall doe verie well, to ſe them ſeverelie puniſhed, who have by their attempts to bring peoperie into that Church occaſioned much trouble in that Kingdome we uſe to blame ſuch as ſet the houſe on ſyer, &amp; not the good people which ſeeke to quench it: ſo &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>here, occaſioned as is pretended, upon the introduction of the Service-booke; Booke of Canons, &amp;c. thereby fearing inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Religion and Lawes.</hi> At this his Majeſtie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <hi>to greeve to ſee them runne headlong into ruine.</hi> Yet out of his innative indulgence to his people, he deſires to <hi>reclay me them from their faults in a faire way: Rather then let them periſh in the ſame. And for further clearing of ſcruples he promiſeth not hereafter to preſſe the practice of the ſaid Service. booke &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, but in a faire and legall way,</hi>
                  <note n="(b)" place="margin">That which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>omaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lawfullie be vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in any way what ſoever: now there is nothing more ſure, then that the <hi>ſervice booke &amp; booke of can:</hi> are <hi>accurſed thinges,</hi> and therefore ought not to be rged or received by any. He that drinkes povſen out ofa goulden cup, kils himſelfe aſſoon as if he tooke it our of an Iron or Wodden Veſſell: So Superſtition brought into the Church in a plauſible and peaceable way, is as deadly a poyſon vnto the receivers of it, as if they were compelled and forced to take it.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>for the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion</hi> he will rectifie it<note n="(c)" place="margin">It is as poſſible to waſh the <hi>Black-moore vvhite.</hi> As by any rectifications to make the high commiſſion a lawfull court. If his Majeſtie, doe take the adviſe of his Council about it, I am ſure (if they be not Bb: or Atheſts or Papiſts.) they wil Counſell him to pull it all down, for there is not one ſtone in that building which God allowes.</note> with the helpe and advile of the privy Counſell, &amp;c. And for geuerall Aſſemblies and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſhalbe indicted and called with his conveniency.</p>
               <p>In concluſion, he requires and hartely wiſheth all is good Subjects not to ſuffer themſelves to be ſeduced and miſled under Religion into diſobedience, and draw on infinitely to his greefe their owne ruine. Which he hath and ſtill ſhall ſtrive to ſave them from ſo long as he ſees not Royall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhaken off.</p>
               <p>The Kings Proclamation beeing publiſhed, the <hi>Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Barrons, Gentlemen, Burrowes, Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> made a Proteſtation againſt it to this effect: 1. That they will conſtantly adhere according to their vocation and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to their Reformation at firſt. Notwithſtanding of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations introduced either of old or late.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17436:12"/>
               <p n="2">2. That they will adhere to their ſupplications given in at Aſſemblies and Parliaments, againſt the <hi>Service-booke, Booke of Cannons the High Commiſſion, &amp;c.</hi> 3. That they will adhere, with their hearts<note n="(a)" place="margin">As I rejoyce to ſee ſuch conſtancy in the Scotſmen, ſo it greeves me to the heart, to think what reeds ſhaken with the wind our people generally are. As <hi>Ioab</hi> after he had fought many battles bravely &amp; ſtoutly; yet died himſelſe at laſt in ſhame &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace; Even ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Preachers &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, having a while refuſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formitie to the Beaſt, have afterwards baſely yeelded to the Bb. and ſo gone to their graves, with ſhame &amp; diſhonour</note> to their Oath and ſubſcription of the <hi>Confeſsion of Faith.</hi> 4. That this Proclamation or Act of Councill or any other Act or Proclamation, &amp;c. ſhall no wayes be prejudiciall<note n="(b)" place="margin">If it be held a baſe thing among men not to keepe a mans Word &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, it is much worſe to breake Covenant with the Lord, yet ſo doe all thoſe, who promiſe to feare God, and doe his worke in his owne way, and yet doe the commaundements of the Prelates.</note> to <hi>the Confeſsion of Faith.</hi> Lawes and Liberties of their Kingdome, nor to their ſupplications Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meetings, &amp;c. 5. Seeing their Supplications, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, are delayed and in effect refuſed, whatſoever trouble or inconvenience fall out in the Land in the meane time, for want of thoſe ordinary remedies, not to be imputed to them.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, they proteſt that it ſhalbe Lawfulll for them, to defend and maintaine that Religion, Lawes, and Liberties of their Kingdome, the <hi>Kings</hi> authority in defence thereof, and every one of them one another in that cauſe, of meantaining the Religion and the Kings fore-ſaid authority, according to their power, vocation, and Covenant, with bodies, lives, meanes, &amp;c. againſt all perſuits whatſoever, or againſt all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall or internall invaſions, menaced in this Proclamation. 6. They proteſt, that their former Supplications, meeting, and mutual defences, are to be commended as real duties of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubjects,<note n="(c)" place="margin">Que. Whether England hath not as much Previledge, to reject the <hi>Service-book &amp; Canons, High Commiſſion,</hi> and all other ſuch like Idolitries, and to eſtabliſh &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the true worſhip of God, as hath Scotland.</note> and not to be ſtiled <hi>great diſorders, miſdeame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, blinde diſobedience, under pretext of Religion and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning headlong into ruine, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17436:13"/>
               <p>In concluſion they exſpect that his Majeſty will preſently indict theſe ordinary remedies of a free Aſſemblie and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament to their iuſt ſupplications, which may be exſpected from ſo iuſt and gracious a King.<note n="(a)" place="margin">When the men of Iſreel were offended with their Brethren, for that they had brought the K. his Houſehold over <hi>&amp; Iordan, Iudah</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; <hi>the</hi> K. <hi>is neere of Kin to us. Wherefore then be yee angry for this matter?</hi> This may ſerve as a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why the <hi>Scots</hi> are firſt in bringing the King home from his enemies the Bb. <hi>the</hi> K. <hi>is neere of kin to them.</hi> Now, for the State of England, if they have any zeale of God, and love to the King, they will fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this good worke of <hi>Iudah</hi> ſo happily begunne for the Kings ſafety and honour.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This don <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of Caffles <hi>&amp;c,</hi> in the name of the Noblemen, Maſter <hi>Alexander Gipſon</hi> younger of <hi>Durie,</hi> in name of the Barrones, Maſter <hi>Iohn Ker</hi> Miniſter at <hi>Salt. Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun,</hi> in name of the Miniſters, and Maſter <hi>Archbald Iohnston,</hi> Reader hereof, in name of all who adheres to the Confeſſion of Faith, &amp; Covenant lately renewed within this Kingdome, Tooke Inſtruments in the Hands of three Notars preſent, at the ſaid mercat croſſe in <hi>Edenburgh;</hi> beeing invironed with Numbers of the aforeſaid Noblemen, Barons, Gentlemen, Borrows, Miniſters and Commons, Before many Hundred witneſſes; &amp; craved the extract thereof: And in token of their dutifull reſpect to his Majeſty; confidence of the equity of their cauſe and innocencie of their carriage, and hope of his Majeſties gratious acceptance, They offred in humility, with ſubmiſe reverence, a Copy thereof to the Herauld.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being ended the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> leaves <hi>Eden;</hi> and goes back to London, now what followed touching thoſe afaires you ſhall-know in the next part</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Rev. <hi>18.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Reward her even as ſhee rewardeth you: and double vnto her double according to her workes: in the cup which ſhee hath filled, fill to her double:</p>
               </q>
               <pb facs="tcp:17436:13"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
